We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
A century ago, the age of first
menstruation averaged as late as nearly 17.
So, why is sexual maturity
coming so much earlier now?
Here’s our first story.
Healthy Seventh-day Adventist
vegetarians
may be longest living,
but might that come at a cost?
A semen analysis
at a fertility clinic
in Loma Linda, California,
home to a large population
of Adventists,
raised questions
about their sperm quality.
Though still within
the normal range,
vegetarians had about
a 25 percent lower sperm count.
The few vegans tested also had
a lower sperm concentration,
but they made up for that
with their 30 percent
greater ejaculate volume.
The vegans did have
significantly fewer
activated sperm, though,
which is a sign
of decreased fertility.
The researchers suggested
soy consumption
as a possible mechanism,
as Adventist vegetarians
in California
average
about a half serving a day
of plant-based meats,
many of which contain soy.
Soy phytoestrogens have been
put to the test, though,
and months of consuming
up to the equivalent of nearly
20 servings of soy a day
did not result
in any adverse effects
on sperm parameters.
There were only five vegans
in the study,
so the sperm quality findings
could just be a fluke,
but if verified,
this could reflect
an evolutionary trade-off
between fertility and lifespan
first proposed
nearly a century ago.
Using a finely tuned laser,
it's possible to selectively
destroy individual cells
as the tiny roundworm
C. elegans develops,
and terminating the cells
that give rise
to sperm and eggs
significantly extends lifespan.
The same phenomenon can be
demonstrated in fruit flies,
potentially shifting
the body's priorities
from reproduction to survival.
The fertility
versus longevity trade-off
may be one of the reasons why
spaying and neutering
our pets
can extend their lives.
Based on a study
of millions of dogs and cats,
sterilized dogs
live about 20 percent longer
than "intact" dogs,
and spayed cats
live about 40 percent longer,
and neutered cats
a remarkable 60 percent longer.
What about men
who have been castrated?
Eunuchs seem to live
25 percent longer
than non-castrated men.
Up until the 1950s
in the United States,
the so-called "feebleminded"
were involuntary sterilized
by the state
in a eugenics program
upheld by none other than
Oliver Wendell Holmes,
who wrote for the majority
on the Supreme Court:
"[S]ociety can prevent those
who are manifestly unfit
from continuing their kind.
The principle that sustains
compulsory vaccination
is broad enough to cover
cutting the Fallopian tubes."
The heinous practice
of compulsory sterilization
did allow for
a natural experiment, though,
and one mental institution
found that castrated men
lived about 14 years longer
than intact men
in the same hospital.
A genealogy database
of nearly 200,000 men and women
across three centuries
in 16 countries
found that those
who had fewer children
seemed to live longer.
Centenarians, for example,
were found
to have fewer children
at later ages.
This is not to suggest
that having fewer children
will make you live longer,
but rather
that constitutional factors
that enhance human lifespan
may come at the expense
of reduced
reproductive potential,
another example of the
antagonistic pleiotropy theory
I talked about before.
For example, selection
for lifespan extension
in model organisms can lead
to longer lived animals
but with reduced
reproductive capacity.
It makes intuitive sense
when you consider the context
of food scarcity.
In lean times, it makes sense
to put off reproduction
until the return
of more favorable conditions
to ensure long-term survival.
In the infamous
Minnesota Starvation Study
that used conscientious
objectors as guinea pigs
during World War II,
the study subjects
rapidly lost their libidos
after their calorie intake
was cut in half.
As one of them put it,
"I have no more sexual feeling
than a sick oyster."
The same calorie restriction
that extends
the lives of animals
can also cause a reduction
in the number of progeny.
If you read my book
How Not to Age,
you'll be familiar
with the nutrient-sensing
aging pathways--
IGF-1, mTOR, AMPK--
that create kind of a seesaw
between tissue acceleration
and reproduction on one side
and tissue preservation
and rejuvenation on the other.
Thankfully, we can shift
the weight
to a more optimal balance
with diet.
The later girls
start their periods,
the longer they tend to live.
Each year later is associated
with significantly lower risk
of dying from heart disease
and stroke, plateauing out
with the lowest
overall mortality
among those who don't start
menstruating until age 15.
Isn't 15 a little late?
It didn't used to be.
A century ago,
the age of first menstruation
averaged as late as nearly 17.
Similarly, the age
of breast development
has dropped an average of
about three months per decade
over the last half century
around the world,
down to 9 or 10 years old
in the United States,
necessitating a change
in textbook definitions
of quote-unquote
"premature" puberty.
Earlier breast development
(before age 10 versus 12 or 13)
is associated
with as much as 23 percent
greater breast cancer risk
later in life,
and each year later
a girl starts to menstruate
is linked
to significantly lower risk
of cancers of the uterus,
liver, skin,
bladder, colon, lung,
and breast.
Thankfully, the age of puberty
is something
over which we have
a degree of control.
Higher levels of IGF-1
are associated
with earlier sexual maturity,
so it's no surprise that girls
eating more animal protein
experience puberty
significantly earlier,
an effect not seen
with protein from plants.
A meta-analysis of 16 studies
on diet and development
found that one's first period
appears to start earlier
by two months
for each additional
one gram per day
of animal protein intake
in childhood.
So, for example,
at seven years old,
girls consuming more than
12 servings of meat a week
had 75 percent greater odds
of menstruating
within the next five years
or so
compared to girls at that age
eating less than
four servings a week,
and this relationship was seen
for both red meat
and poultry consumption.
IGF-1 and other aging pathways
may not fully explain
these findings, however,
as persistent pollutants
that build up in meat, like DDT,
have also been linked
to precocious puberty.
In our last story,
we look at how the early
onset of puberty in girls
may be due to endocrine-disrupting
chemical pollutants in the meat supply.
“Early onset of puberty is
considered a…risk factor…
[for] a number of diseases in adulthood,
including hormone-related cancers,
[a shorter lifespan], metabolic
syndrome, and cardiovascular disease.”
The conventional thinking
has been that the reason the
age of puberty has been
getting earlier and earlier
is because our children have been
getting fatter and fatter.
Well, our kids have been getting heavier,
especially in the United States—
we’re #1!
But, while the age of a girl’s first period
has been dropping in the U.S. and Asia,
in Europe—despite their kids
getting heavier, too—
there hasn’t been a steady
decline in puberty onset.
So, maybe it’s less about
how much kids are eating,
and more about
what they’re eating.
The most consistent link between
diet and premature puberty
has been animal protein consumption.
For example, every gram of
daily animal protein intake—
that’s the weight of a paperclip—
has been associated with about
a 17% increase in the risk
of girls starting their periods
earlier than age 12.
Why this link between animal protein
and premature puberty?
Well, we know meat increases the
levels of the growth hormone IGF-1,
and that alone is associated
with early-onset puberty.
But, maybe animal protein is just a
proxy for the endocrine-disrupting
chemicals that build up the
food chain in animal products.
Recent reports found
“significant associations
between exposure to
environmental pollutants
and sexual maturation.”
This was done over in Europe.
In the U.S.,
a similar relationship was found
with the flame-retardant chemicals,
for example,
which are found mostly in poultry
and fish, unless you’re eating cat food.
“Over the last three decades,
human exposure
[to these levels of industrial pollutants]
in the U.S. have increased
from virtually nonexistent to
[almost everyone carrying
them around now].”
They appear to have
multiple adverse effects,
but of all the potential toxicities,
endocrine disruption
(meaning hormonal disruption)
may be the main
concern in children.
Girls with the most circulating in their
bloodstream appeared up to ten times
more likely to start
their periods early.
But, since these chemicals are found
most concentrated in fish and chicken,
maybe the level of these
chemicals in their bloodstream
is just kind of a proxy
for their meat consumption.
Whatever the reason,
animal protein intake
is associated with
early-onset puberty,
whereas plant protein
has the opposite effect.
Children with higher levels of
vegetable proteins starting puberty
seven months later than average,
and children eating more animal protein
may start puberty seven months
earlier than average.
Soy seems most protective.
“[G]irls with the highest levels
of dietary isoflavone intake
[the phytonutrients in soy foods]
may experience their onset
of breast development…
approximately 7 or 8 months later than
girls with the lowest levels of intake.”
What effect might these shifts
have on disease rates?
Well, delays in the timing of puberty
in response to beneficial dietary habits
(higher intakes of vegetable protein and
soy, and lower intakes of animal protein)
“may be of substantial
public health relevance.”
A later age of starting one’s period
is related to a reduced risk
of breast cancer,
and a later first period is associated
with lower total mortality
(meaning a longer lifespan).”
Hence, “a delay in the timing of puberty
by approximately 7-8 months,” which is
“achievable with dietary modifications”
—either more plants or fewer animals—”
may translate into about a 6%
reduction in breast cancer risk,”
and up to a 3%
decrease in total mortality.
And, it’s not just a problem in girls;
boys eating more meat in childhood
appear to be more likely to grow up
with the kind of abdominal fat deposits
that increase risk
for heart disease.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.